hey guys Shan this side and welcome to
concept and coding today I will be
covering very very important topic and
very frequently Asked Topic in an
interview which is nothing but an
exception handling so apart from just
controller advice and response status
annotation I will covering a lot more
things and I hope you will find it
really really helpful in your interviews
and your day-to-day work
also so let's start what all the classes
involved in handling an exception so
here if you see this is an hierarchy of
classes and out of this hierarchy this
five 1 2 3 so these three
resolver is very important and this four
and five this four and five are
generally a helper classes I considered
as an helper classes so these five
classes are very important in handling
an exception and at top we have an
interface Handler exception resolver
which is an interface which expose a
method I think do
resolve
exception
okay so let's understand the sequence
when an exception occurs and the role of
each five
classes so now let's say that you
already know that the first controller
which spring boot provide to us is
nothing but a dispatcher subet so
dispatcher subet is the one which
actually invokes our controller
also so it is is possible that our
controller might throw an exception or
dispatcher not able to invoke our
controller itself so in any case let's
say any case exception
occurs what would happen so dispatcher
subet will pass the request to this
Handler exception resolver composite
class okay so this is this class Handler
exception resolver composite class
so this class I considered as mostly an
Helper and most probably you can say
that
orchestrator orchestrator of what
orchestrator of this resolver so there
are three resolvers exception Handler
exception resolver class second is
response status exception resolver and
third is default Handler exception
resolver this three these three are
resolver so here this class Handler
exception resolver composite class
invoke this resolver in
sequence first will be invoked this
second this and third this so here what
happen is whenever an exception happens
so this exception is passed to the first
resolver this is your first resolver
exception Handler exception resolver so
once this resolver process its work the
control goes back to your composite
class then it check hey exception is
handled if yes if this resolver is able
to handle your exception then it will
not grow further it will return to this
one default error attribute class but
now let's say that if the handle if the
exception is not handled then this
composite class will pass it to the your
second resolver which is response status
exception
resolver and after that again before
proceeding to the next resolver it again
check hey is your previous resolver is
able to handle the exception if yes then
you know that it will goes to this step
default error
attribute if no then only it will goes
to the third and last resolver default
Handler exception
resolver okay and once all the three
resolver complete its
task ultimately the control again comes
to default error attribute so no matter
whether any resolver is able to handle
it or not ultimately the control will
have to become come here if they are
able to handle it then directly will
come it will not go to further resolver
otherwise it will pass through all the
resolver one resolver two and finally
resolver three after that again the
control comes to
this so and after this the response has
been send to the client so at this point
of time you would be clear that
these three are the resolvers classes
which actually handles an
exception it is followed in sequence
this is First Response status exception
resolver is second and default is third
and this two are the helper classes this
is nothing but an orchestrator which
actually orchestrate this three resolver
classes and after that this is the last
one which
actually create a
response with proper
status time stem what is the message
proper error response and ultimately
send the response so this is ultimately
where we create a response actually what
is your status what is error message
status let's say 400 error message is
let's say bad request something and
ultimately the response is
sent okay let's see a flow with an
example this will clarify you more so I
have created a very simple controller
class okay I have one rest controller
class get mapping means it is/ API SL
get hyphen user API I'm creating it and
I'm throwing null pointer exception and
throwing one message throwing null
pointer exception for
testing if you run this what output you
will see I am hitting this API what
output I will see 500 error code
and here time stamp status 500 error
internal server error and
path
how who set all these things I I never
said here that it's a 500 internal error
code but somewhere internally it has
been set who we will see that just one
more
example creating a one more controller
but here now I am
throwing new custom exception
okay you in Java I have already
explained you how you can create a your
custom exception so I created a custom
exception I extended runtime exception
class okay and I have just exposed two
Fields here status and message in the
Constructor I'm setting this field and
the getter
method okay so here if you see that I am
throwing new custom exception setting
this let it's a bad request and this is
the message request is not correct user
ID is missing so I'm setting a status
and
message and I'm throwing this now if you
run this hit this API what output you
are seeing again 500 internal server
error the time stem current time stem
let's say
status error path now here if you see
the 500 internal server error now if you
see that hey you are returning bad
request which is nothing but a 400 and
messages request is not correct user ID
is missing but why this seems 500
internal server error is coming what is
happening
here one thing you need to consider that
in both the
example we are not creating response
entity
object we are just returning the
exception so some other class is
creating the response entity object so
from the previous video you already know
that whenever we send a response we have
to create a response entity object okay
in that we set two things body and
status but here if you see that we are
just returning an
exception but it's still in an output we
are seeing this response so somebody is
creating
response entity for us who I think you
already know the answer right who it's
actually default error attribute
but why 500 why 500 so here what
happening is when you are throwing an
exception and not returning response
entity means you are utilizing the
exception resolver framework now your
all the exception will pass through this
flow okay if none of the resolver is
able to handle your exception then this
default error attribute by default value
it will set
500 okay so 500 is nothing but a default
status
code okay
but if you want full
control and don't want to rely on
exception resolver then we have to
create the response entity object always
remember and here the example which I
showing you many Company still follows
this they don't rely on exception
resolver so what happened is here the
same thing I am throwing custom
exception status and message very basic
okay this is your custom exception class
and just uh just to recap you this
message is just uh optional you can even
send
super super
message so this runtime exception its
parent is exception
class this has I think one field called
detailed
message okay so this detailed message is
somewhere which uh the framework wanted
this message is ultimately get set to
this one so either two way either you
just do super message okay and
ultimately it will go to runtime
exception runtime exception here if you
see uh let's go runtime exception
here again it says super
message and here ultimately it gets set
into detailed message okay this is one
way or if I don't want to do super just
for clarity purpose I just
added
here I just added a string message
setting it and override the get message
itself and returning this message here
itself okay instead of uh if you don't
want to override it then you have to do
super and pass the
message and UL Ely this message will get
set to that uh detailed message field
this one and then if framework call get
message this one this detailed message
would be return but if you don't want it
I already told you that uh you can
override this one you can override it
and return this message okay so this is
just a quick recap like uh so now come
back to this one I am doing a try
throwing an exception sending an status
and
message now I am catching one I am
catching this custom exception and
another I am catching this generic
exception so definitely this custom
exception will get caught this throw new
exception now here if you see I am
returning the response entity I am
creating the response entity body and
your
status so body I am sending is I'm
creating an
object object which has this error
response is just nothing but a pojo
class which has three things time stem
message and Status very simple so I'm
creating a new object which is nothing
but a pojo I'm setting the date current
date what is the message so whatever the
exception is
coming okay I'm doing e. get message so
message would be said and whatever the
status code E.G status okay so this
status would be set into this object and
this object I'm putting into the body
and then the response what is the
response status I said this e doget
status this one only so this is how your
response going to look like the 400 bed
request which is response entity status
and this is your body time stem status
and message this one time stem status
and
message so now here if you see that this
resolver I told right three resolvers
are there those are not even involved
now you have taken control how you are
going to handle an exception custom
exception happens how you want to handle
it so you have created a response entity
and it got return properly you are able
to see proper error messages which you
wanted to
return exception resolver is not
invoked but when we don't return
response entity we just simply return
throw somebody has to create response
entity for us that's where the framework
comes into the picture and that's where
this all resolver and flow comes into
the picture now I already told you now
when you throw custom exception so this
composite will pass this
custom exception to this class resolver
the
first exception Handler ex exception
Handler exception resolver says that hey
I only able to handle at
theate controller
advice and at
theate exception Handler annotation
apart from this I don't know so does
custom exception has any such annotation
no so this say that I can't handle it it
goes here does exception handled by
previous resolver no so it goes to the
response status exception resolver hey
can you handle this custom exception
it says that hey I only take care of at
theate
response status annotation I don't know
about anything else again it goes
here hey does this resolve it does able
to handle this custom exception no then
it goes to the default one if you go to
the default one default one is very like
here if you see default Handler
exception disolver class it has very
predefined that okay it handle spring
framework related issues like method not
found media type not supported right
missing parameter exception so it only
able to handle predefined exceptions so
will it understand custom exception no I
don't understand this and ultimately all
three resolver pass and control comes to
here and default error attribute what it
will do here if you see default error
attribute it will pass it will put time
stem current
status now nobody able to handle it so
default status would be set as
500 and all other details would be set
path error details and it will
return the response entity the response
entity would be created with this object
and
return if any of the resolver is able to
handle the exception then they will just
set status and message
okay now let's say that just assume that
exception Handler exception resolver is
able to handle the custom exception
let's say it will just send that okay
for this exception this is the status
message let's say 400 this is the
message it will just set this and then
it will say that yes handle it will
close here it will not proceed further
and default error attribute will set
proper status not default one 400 proper
message and then return it
so you got the flow so here if you see
that default error attribute set this
attribute time stamp status everything
and then once the attribute is created
it will create a response entity with
body and status and
return
okay so I'll show you let's see now
let's say this is an example where I am
having a controller same very basic I'm
throwing a custom exception bad request
user ID is missing see I am not
returning response entity I'm just
throwing it
directly if I run it let me debug
it I started the debuger point now let's
say we are hitting it get
user okay where the control comes
composite first now here in the
composite you will see the resolver it
will iterating it
it will itting it all the resolvers so
now here if you see
resolvers three resolver first is
exception second is response status
third is default
one okay so if we assume the this custom
exception will goes to
now your exception Handler exception
resolver the first Handler the first
resolver it will not be able to resolve
it so it will goes to the second
resolver which is response status
exception
resolver response status exception
resolver is also not able to handle it
then it will goes to the third one your
default handle exception
resolver so in the default one no one
would be able to handle
it ultimately it goes to the default
error attribute and what is the status
it will
send so here if you see in the
attributes the status it will set to 500
internal server error because no
resolver is able to handle
it no resolver is able to handle it and
ultimately you see 500 internal server
error okay that's why we saw this
message so now question is what
exception does this three resolver
handles okay we know the flow we know
the sequence we know the reason if we
throw an exception if it is not handled
I will get 500 default
value but what this
resolver handles actually I don't want
to use custom let's say you don't want
to use this you don't want to handle in
each you know that there are so many
methods there are so many controllers do
in each class in each controller in each
method you want to do try catch and
handle the exception
if it is a small application it yes it's
good but if it's a huge
application it's mostly you will find
it's a code duplicate for the same
custom exception you have to send a
status error message and different
different
places so we can take use of the
framework but before that we need to
understand what this three resolver
actually
handles let's start with the first one
exception Handler exception resolver
it is responsible for handling below
annotation exception Handler annotation
and controller advice
annotation so now let's go to the
exception Handler first but it's a
controller level exception handling
controller level so by the name itself
it should be clear I have one
controller user controller inside this I
might have multiple methods get
method now I don't have to worry about
doing try catch and everything if any my
business logic if any exception comes I
will throw it if any business validation
comes I will throw the
exception now in the controller level
each controller I can put
this
method handle let's say c for custom
exception handling I put one method
handle custom
exception put an
annotation at theate exception Handler
what is this annotation right what what
this ex uh exception it handles so we
will write it
here so what would happen here is that
whenever in this controller no matter
how many methods you have currently here
I have only one method even if you have
methods out of those 10 methods anybody
throws custom exception this Handler
would catch
it okay this Handler will say that okay
this Handler is for handling the custom
exception so this method will get
involved okay the same custom exception
it catches here and then it we can
create our response entity how you going
to handle it so I'm creating a response
entity here that hey whatever the
exception is coming read its message
read its
status okay so this is the status I want
to
set so now here if you see that this is
body right
this is body and this body is x. get
message this is a string so response
entity I'm returning a string and if you
see the
response 400 bad request which is this
status and the body is your message uh
string so that's why only string comes
no Json response you saw No Object so
user ID is
missing
okay another use case just to show
returning error response object instead
of just message like same thing let's
say you are in a single controller no
matter how many method you have anybody
throws custom exception I have written
one exception Handler which takes care
of custom exception so this method would
get
involed and this custom exception what
I'm uh returning a response entity with
this error response this is my body now
which I'm creating an
object object the same thing I have
already showed you right time message
and Status so
date message exception. getet message
exception. get status so this three will
get set and I will set into this body
and in the response what is the status
response status I set this
only now you see the response 400 bed
request and now instead of just a string
you are getting a
object Okay so now this is your body
right so I that's why I written use
object here in the
response just see one more use case to
show multiple exception Handler in one
single
controller so I have written two method
here one get
method one API is throwing custom
exception another is throwing let's say
illegal argument
exception and the same controller I have
now added two exception Handler
one which takes care of custom exception
another takes care of illegal argument
exception so I have written so this
method you can change
handle something you can give some name
uh illegal argument exception
method so any this exception whenever
this exception is thrown custom
exception from any method you know that
which exception Handler will get
involved any illegal illegal argument
exception would be thrown you know which
exception will get uh which exception
Handler will get caught just see one
more use case use case to show one
exception Handler handling multiple
exceptions so now if you see above hey
both are doing the same thing let's
say this custom exception is also
nothing but a bad request illegal
argument exception is nothing but a bad
request and message we are anywhere
reading from the exception we can even
generalize it right so you can also do
this add theate custom exception Handler
and then you can make it an array kind
of thing custom exception or illegal
argument exception anything which occurs
this Handler will get invoked and
response entity this is the message I
will set body and this is the status bad
request okay so that also is possible
one more use case let's see that here
now I am not returning response ENT
okay I am not returning response entity
I am
returning I am just setting the response
and let the default error attribute
create a response entity for me so here
if you see that the same part two
methods now in the exception
Handler which takes care of only custom
exception I am here it you see that I'm
not returning response entity I am just
now here if you see that HTTP subet
response I am accepting in the
parameter in the response I have put
like what is the status and what is the
message I just set this two value two
attributes in the
response now when the control goes to
default error attribute you know that it
will look for status and
message now since our exception Handler
the first resolver would be able to
handle it okay so we have already said
bad request and message okay in the
response so it will get bad request and
proper message I will show you okay so
but here remember that one question
should comes to your mind that hey
Shan first I have seen that when we are
handling a custom
exception only one parameter was
there
exception now here I'm
seeing two parameter sttp subet response
also comes in so what all parameters
this method can take which is annotated
with exception
Handler so you can have HTTP sulet
response HTTP solet
request and
exception if you have only one if your
exception Handler is accepting only one
or taking care of only one exception you
can write exact same
exception here but here if you if you
exception Handler annotation is taking
care of more than one exception then you
have to use the parent level here in
this case I'm using exception
class okay so the third parameter you
can use is exception and you can use in
any order even I can use custom
exception first and HTTP sub response
second so here if you go I'll show
you here if you go in exception Handler
exception
resolver so here inside that it would be
like invoke and handle invoke for
request get argument
values here if you see see that it has
something called resolve
argument so it so it already knows that
what are the supported parameter it
has okay so if you pass this it knows
that what value it has to fill this if
you pass this it knows what value it has
to fill so you can use it in any order
and if you don't use it if you use it
either one or all three it would be
fine okay but you can't just put like a
string
this class doesn't know how to support
this parameter how to fill this string
so then it would not even invoke so here
I just wanted to use response because in
the HTTP subet response I want to set
the status and the body so that when my
control reaches to default error
attribute it knows this field let's see
that so here in this
one I am writing one exception Handler
public let's say I don't want to return
anything handle
custom exception and this Handler I'm
writing for handling custom exception
only custom exception and also I want
HTTP subet response also you can put
request also but I don't currently need
the request so now here I am setting
response. send error so it set two two
things right one is I think int is your
status code and then your message so
status code I want to set let's say uh
here whatever the exception this one so
exception. get status.
value and exception. get message and it
has to throw in IO okay now if we run
this what would
happen so now first your controller get
invoked and it throws an exception once
an exception is thrown you know that
dispatcher subet will pass it to
composite
class okay now this composite class will
first pass it to exception Handler
exception
resolver now it will see that
hey this
exception is there any exception Handler
annotation present which can takes care
of this
exception okay now it is checking now
here it is checking that yes it is
invoking and handling so here
our C exception Handler got invoke now
here I have handled it either you can
return response entity here itself then
once you return a response entity then
it will not go to your default attribute
but here I am just setting the response
what what is the status what is the
message that's
all I am not uh returning the response
entity but I just send the response
attributes now after this one the
control goes to your default error
attribute which is setting time stem now
status what status it will send
C
400 okay and it will also set the
message user ID is missing and
ultimately it will create a response
entity and
return
okay got it
so I think you should be very clear that
when you returning response entity
default attribute is not comes into the
picture but now here I am returning just
setting the attributes in the response
then default attribute comes into the
picture and then it is creating this
object but I think exception Handler is
clear to you right now let's see global
exception handling so now let's say that
what happen if there are you have
hundred of controllers let's say and
everywhere you have to handle the custom
exception in a similar way doesn't each
class each controller you have to write
this method again it's a code duplicate
right then where the global exception
handling comes into the
picture so how you can create a Global
exception handling so I can create a new
class annotate it with atate controller
advice okay which tells this resolver
that yes this is a global exception
Handler and you should take care of it
and inside this we can write the similar
way the way the way we are writing a
method here right the same thing you can
do it here also nothing no
difference only thing is this class is
now applicable for more than one
controller even user controller maybe uh
some invoice controller order controller
any exception happens let's say custom
exception okay the first priority would
be given to that hey any exception
Handler which can handle the custom
exception is present in your controller
no then it will go and check into the
global one which is annotated with
controller
advice okay so let's say that if any
exception happens it will properly
invoke
this and I told you like what if I
provide both controller level and Global
level exception which has more priority
so here I have provided the same custom
exception
Handler at controller level and also at
the global level and if any exception
occurs through new custom
exception which Handler will invoke it
this or this
so user ID is missing from controller
exception hand so first priority is
always your controller
level here controller level and then if
not then it goes to the global okay and
then in global it checks the same
exception
Handler also one more question is what
if there are two Handler which can
handle an
exception which one will give priority
now here if you see that in the in the
Global itself I have two exception
Handler one is custom exception docl
class another is runtime exception docl
class now if this exception is thrown
you know that uh ultimately your
exception resolver will comes into the
picture the first resolver and that will
use this annotation and knows that okay
there are two methods one is this method
which can handle this exception but it
is exactly matching custom exception
custom exception
another is runtime exception one but it
is also parent of this one it can also
runtime exception also can handle this
but which one to then use so it will use
a hierarchy first priority to the exact
matching one if there is no exact
matching one then it goes to the upper
level it's parent okay so currently in
this case I have custom exception so
this will get inv work but let's say in
case if I don't have this then then
response runtime exception will get
invol okay so you got it the first
resolver what it
handles this is
your exception Handler exception
resolver it handles this at theate
exception Handler annotation and at the
rate controller
advice and this is a industry standard
also we use that also in
Industry how you can use either
controller level and either Global level
also
then there is another called response
status exception resolver which is your
second resolver in the
sequence very confusing part many people
will say that it takes care of at theate
response status annotation the correct
definition is it handles uncaught
exception uncaught exception annotated
with response status annotation let's
see the meaning of this definition very
confusing I'll tell you why
see this use
case very simple controller I am
throwing an exception new custom
exception I'm just throwing a message
that's all and very basic custom
exception class
okay extending runtime exception and
here I am not writing my own message
field and overwriting the message method
I just said that super message so
ultimately that message field get filled
up but here if you see I have put a
response status annotation at top of
this custom exception
class what is the status bad request so
now what happen is I am throwing an
exception I am throwing an exception I
am not returning response entity so
control will goes to
resolvers First it will goes to
exception Handler exception resolver
that don't know how to handle custom
exception because there is no at theate
exception Handler which can handle the
custom exception so there is no so it
don't know how to handle this the second
it goes to response status exception
resolver there it will say that okay
custom exception now it goes to custom
exception class and see that hey at
theate response status is there or not
yes it's there so it would handle
it it would be able to handle it so
handle uncaught exception this is
uncaught exception it just going through
resolver one by one can you handle me
can you handle me so okay Only uncaught
Exception this response status able to
handle it always remember that so now in
this case here if I show
you response status exception
resolver okay so here let's say if any
exception
comes
and it able to resolve it let's say uh
status not equals to null then what it
does
it it applies it the same thing what we
do right send error it nothing but it
just set the response HTTP sub response
it just send the
status okay it is also possible to send
a message I will tell you
but you know that resolver will do
resolver will not create response entity
only in the
response it will just set a status and
message and then your default attribute
class create a object out of it so
resolver will say that yes I can handle
this because it has responsive status
and this is the status uh code it taken
from The annotation
so it properly set the response status
so it will send it properly send the
respon status bad
request
okay but here if you see that also
second example of this one the same
thing I am throwing custom exception
this custom exception has annotated with
response
status now apart from status I you can
also send message these only the two
possible things value and response value
is nothing but your status and reason is
your message so here if you see that now
when exception this uncut exception goes
reaches till response status exception
resolver it will know that uh
status okay and it will also say the
reason if reason is also there then it
will send this both status and reason in
the response
okay so it will send this status and
reason both so your status would be sent
and your proper reason would be sent
here okay even though now here if you
see even though my message is this
one but I have it has given more
priority to this
message if you haven't written this
message at the top what message come
user ID is missing this one so this is
nothing but a default
default message would be used by default
error attribute
class okay so if no message is given it
will also not come here but since you
have given the message so this will be
use a default message and the response
status no message was there so it only
set status that time but when you have
given the response
also reason also then it set the status
plus reason and that's where invalid
request pass this comes rather than
this okay now actual one more confusion
comes into the responses status what if
I use above an exception Handler method
till now it is handling uncaught
exception exception happened which is
not nobody caught it and this exception
has this class level response status so
our response status
exception resolver able to handle
it but what if you hand uh use it with
exception Handler now see
this this class controller you have one
get
mapping get user you are throwing an
exception very basic see that in this
custom exception I am not using response
entity here uh not response status
here okay it just a custom exception I
have written one custom uh exception
Handler class exception Handler method
which takes care of this custom
exception also I have put response
status
here okay so what is the response status
bad request and the reason is invalid
request sent and in the method I have
put response entity but here I'm sending
me message you are not authorized
forbidden
so now here if you see that two
different things I'm doing in the
exception Handler it is setting this as
a
status and this as a
body but in the response status I am
sending this as a uh let's say the
message or this as a status so this is
which status will be picked and what is
the flow many times what engineer
confused that okay response status means
it would be handled by our resolver
first is
exception
Handler exception resolver then response
status response resolver so what they do
with this is that okay the first uh
exception happen first control will come
here it will set the status as
forbidden
forbidden and message as you are not
authorized you are not
authorized and after that the control
will comes to here which will set like a
stat which will override it status to
bad
request and reason
as invalid request
send okay so this is wrong understanding
few things are happening in this you
need to understand first thing we are
sending response entity yes the control
first comes to the exception Handler
resolver
here it is creating a response entity
itself so definitely it will not goes to
the second
resolver okay and you already know from
the uh if you goes to the first diagram
itself
sequence this
one anytime before even going to the
second resolver it first check hey does
exception was handled by the previous
resolver exception Handler it won't go
to the next resolver
itself so here in this
scenario so here in this scenario
exception Handler is able to handle the
custom exception so the control will
never goes to the response status
resolver okay it will be here it will be
handled by this only and it's creating a
response entity itself and if you run
this what output you will see you will
see 400 bad
request status is this message is this
invalid request send now the where
problem comes hey sh you are saying
that response
status will not get
invoked then shouldn't this forbidden
should have come why this uh bad request
is coming this one response status one
who is handling this if this not this
resolver so here if you see it is
handled by your spring uh flow itself a
spring framework itself so see this
one exception Handler exception resolver
first it invoke it it handles it
whatever the return value return value
is your response entity itself okay
after this it is handling the status
response so no no resolve is handling it
see the class sulet invocable Handler
method it is spring framework which
handles the response status afterward it
okay so whatever you have set forbidden
and this it got override by this
responses status by Spring framework
itself not by
resolver resolver control will not even
go because exception Handler takes care
of this exception itself so understand
it very clearly that don't mix response
resolver once a resolver one particular
resolver is handled it second resolver
will not get
involved and once you mix this response
status with exception Handler you need
to only understand that it only takes
care of uncaught exception means this is
exception is not handled by exception
Handler then it comes
here then only it will handle it
uncaught exception but this one custom
exception is already handled by
exception
Handler okay so but response entity is
uh response status is
there
after exception Handler exception
resolver it's gives the priority to
responses status so it's get override
with this
value okay so exception Handler
exception resolver the same thing I
showed you you can check the code that
the response status is done by sping
framework not by the response status
response
resolver again one more thing you will
again scratch your head now what would
be the output of this can you answer
this so here if you see
that the same I writing one exception
Handler same but only difference is I am
now not returning response entity I am
just setting the status and the message
into the response like through response.
send error and setting the status and
message in the response and also I have
response status which is bad request so
what it will print forbidden or bad
request when the custom exception comes
so custom exception
comes it would be caught by the first
resolver
itself now this uh exception Handler
exception
resolver it will set this forbidden
response. send error then as per our
previous understanding it would get
override by this and we will say that
bad request but here if you see that
what it's coming 500 internal server
error why because here if you see that I
am not returning response entity I am
doing response. send error when you do
response. send error right what happen
is let's say that
user response. send error what it does
is it set the status it set the message
and it commit
also okay so it committed the response
is committed now you can't change it so
now after that the code AS from the code
itself we know that the framework after
you done it our spring framework would
Now set to uh do response status and it
will now also try to do here if you see
what that class subet right so there it
will do yeah so after this one it will
try to do set response status it is
spring framework not
resolver again it will do the same thing
send error the same
thing it will again try to do commit so
you can't commit a again you will it
will throw an exception so your
exception Handler exception resolver
throws exception itself and that
ultimately Ely turns out to be an
internal server error let's see that
I'll show
you so here in the exception Handler I
am setting the response but now let's
say that I am putting at
theate response
status and uh value I would say that
HTTP bad request or let's
say bad request
and reason I will
put uh invalid request
sent and in the response status let's
say I am
setting instead of exception reading
from exception let's say I'll put just
for proper differentiation HTTP St
forbidden and the message user ID is
missing exception
one now let's see start the debugger
and put one debugger point at that sulet
one
also this
one let's hit
it so first I'm throwing an
exception once an exception is thrown re
control reach to the our Al
composite now after that exception
Handler our method exception Handler got
invoked it set the error so now this
will
committed this will
committed now after that response status
now here if you see I'll put
uh here let me put debugger Point here
we have both right I think control
should come over here so here it try to
do send error again as soon as it will
do send error see exception comes inside
exception Handler exception resolver
itself
so when ultimately the uh this default
attributes status is set as internal
error
okay so you also have to take care of
mind like when you are using exception
Handler and response status together use
it wisely so that's why I advise never
to use together exception Handler and
response status together but if let's
say you have to use it like this you
have put an exception Handler custom
exception then put a responsive status
and give them one responsibility either
the method should have got a
responsibility to set a status and
message or give a response status only
one of them you can't put also like
response entity or response. send error
follow one either let response status do
it or either in this code do it because
you know that from the code what
whatever you set inside this method
inside this method it will get override
by response status so either use this or
this to avoid
confusion okay and the third is default
Handler exception resolver this is very
simple like uh here if you
see I am calling certain method which do
not even exist I don't have any API get
hyph user 3223
the
first it will goes to our composite
because our controller even not reach
okay dispatcher supp not able to find
the controller the control comes from
first itself from composite orchestrator
to it will pass through exception
Handler exception resolver then response
stat response resolver and then the
control comes to your default Handler
exception resolver so here it will go
one by
one so what type of exception we are
currently throwing it's a no resource
found exception no resource found so
ultimately it would like this got handle
no resource found okay
and it's the same thing it will do
handle error response it will just send
the error status and message okay for
this exception
so when the control comes here see
status is 401 404 and messages no static
resource get this so this will get set
into the response and then default error
attribute it will set a proper status
and
message okay no resource found this
message so
default so default Handler exception
resolver is just like spring framework
related exception method not found
resource not found likewise okay so I
hope
this exception handling in a spring boot
is
clear you can uh try it out like do with
your hands you will find lot of good
things and if you have more doubts
please feel free to ping me in the
comment section we can discuss more
thank you bye